<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Harness | e-Enquiry]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.stillwell.me/blog/categories/harness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.stillwell.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-07T15:27:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.stillwell.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Stillwell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['Research in the Cloud' Software Carpentry Event Near London This Summer! (2015)]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stillwell.me/blog/2015/04/29/research-in-the-cloud-software-carpentry-event-near-london/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-29T11:19:35+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stillwell.me/blog/2015/04/29/research-in-the-cloud-software-carpentry-event-near-london</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m very excited to announce that for the past month I have been working on the
arrangements for a cloud-oriented
<a href="http://software-carpentry.org">software carpentry</a> event, and we are now ready
to start recruiting for participants! The
<a href="https://harnesscloud.github.io/2015-07-15-feltham/">event</a>, which is going to
be held at the SAP offices in Feltham (near London Heathrow) July 15-17, is
being organized as a dissemination activity for the European FP7
<a href="http://www.harness-project.eu">HARNESS project</a>. At this event we will extend
the standard software carpentry curriculum of task automation, modular
programming, and version control, with additional modules on cloud computing,
including deployment, configuration, and management of virtual machines.
End-user-ready cloud computing software projects supported by the project will
be covered, particularly the <a href="http://www.conpaas.eu/">ConPaaS</a> runtime
environment and the <a href="http://www.xtreemfs.org/">XtreemFS</a> distributed filesystem.
Participants will also learn about programming
<a href="https://www.maxeler.com/technology/dataflow-computing/">Dataflow</a> engines from
Maxeler and how to access the public
<a href="http://www.egi.eu/infrastructure/cloud/">EGI Federated Cloud</a> infrastructure
for research. There will be a keynote on the HARNESS project and how it is
helping to bring the power of heterogeneous accelerators to the cloud.</p>

<p>In addition to the project partners, there will be representatives from
<a href="http://egi.eu">EGI</a> and the
<a href="http://www.softare.ac.uk">Software Sustainability Institute (SSI)</a> present to
teach some of the modules and provide additional support.</p>

<p>Participation is free, but only 40 places are available, so sign up now!</p>

<p>Details, including a link to the Eventbrite signup page, are available at the
event website: <a href="https://harnesscloud.github.io/2015-07-15-feltham/">https://harnesscloud.github.io/2015-07-15-feltham/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DevOps, Systems Administration, and the Culture of Fear]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.stillwell.me/blog/2014/09/29/a-devops-approach-with-ansible-vagrant-and-docker/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-29T13:09:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.stillwell.me/blog/2014/09/29/a-devops-approach-with-ansible-vagrant-and-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today at the <a href="http://www.harness-project.eu">HARNESS project</a> integration team
meeting I gave a brief
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/marklee1977/devops-39666655">presentation</a> wherein I
discussed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">DevOps</a> and some of my favorite
tools, namely <a href="http://ansible.com">Ansible</a>, <a href="http://vagrantup.com">Vagrant</a>,
and <a href="http://docker.io">Docker</a>.</p>

<p>The central thesis of my talk was that a modern devops approach, based in
version-controlled configuration management implemented using industry-standard
deployment tools and making use of continuous integration and rolling updates
is a must for creating robust distributed systems with lots of moving parts.
Interactive configuration of cloud systems and virtual machines leads to
unreproducible, poorly documented, error-prone &ldquo;brittle&rdquo; systems. It is the
equivalent of collaborative authoring of documents by emailing word processor
files, or software version control by having a backup/ directory containing
numbered/dated zip archives. This leads to a &ldquo;culture of fear&rdquo; wherein people
are afraid to try to fix known problems for fear of &ldquo;making things worse&rdquo;, and
every roll out of of a new api or set of features becomes a dreaded nightmare.</p>

<p>Overall, the talk was well received. We also discussed the Vagrant workflow, and
how, while Docker can be used to provision containers that function the same
way as &ldquo;lightweight&rdquo; virtual machines, ideally each container should really
only be running the minimum number of processes, following the single
responsibility principle.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
